<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % CommonEntities SYSTEM "../COMMON_ENTITIES.ent">
%CommonEntities;
]>
<appendix version="5.0" xml:id="app-install-notes" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <!--<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="docbook.css"?>-->
  <title>Installation Notes</title>
  <indexterm><primary>Installation</primary><secondary>Notes on</secondary></indexterm>
  <para> Before proceeding, it is <emphasis>strongly</emphasis> recommended to read <xref linkend="deploy-planning"
      xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle"/> and <xref linkend="install-config" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle"
    />. </para>
  <para>As part of the upgrade process, the first time the OS Lockdown Console process starts, all <emphasis
      role="italic">custom</emphasis> profiles are examined and updated according to the following rules (in the order
    in which they appear): <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Any modules with options that are not &ldquo;named&rdquo; have the options split into &ldquo;named&rdquo;
          options.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The upgrade process ensures that all named options have a value. If a value is <emphasis role="italic"
            >missing</emphasis> from the module, then the default value for that option is used.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para> At no point will the upgrade process add a new module to any custom profile. As mentioned earlier, for users
    running the Standalone edition from the command line, these changes are made as the profile is processed. To make
    the changes permanent, either configure and start the OS Lockdown Console on each Standalone computer, or copy your
    legacy profiles to a box with the OS Lockdown Console, import them, and then copy the updated copies back to each
    Standalone instance. </para>
  <para> As part of the process of adding new modules, the profiles provided with OS Lockdown have been updated where
    appropriate. It is <emphasis role="italic">highly</emphasis> advisable to use the OS Lockdown Console to perform a
    profile comparison between any custom profiles and the appropriate system-provided profile (if your custom profiles
    are modified copies of the system-provided profiles). The profile comparison flags cases where there are different
    modules present in the profiles and where the option values differ between your profile and the system profile. Note
    that modules that had option values added are not flagged. </para>
  <section xml:id="install-pre">
    <title>Pre-Installation Notes</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enterprise Updates - previous versions of OS Lockdown recommended that an Enterprise installation should
          export the OS Lockdown Console database before upgrading, agree (&ldquo;Yes&rdquo;) when the installer asks if
          the update should start with clean directories, and then re-import the database. This is no longer required,
          as the OS Lockdown Console can automatically update the database during the first re-start after the
          update.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>For all installations, existing OS Lockdown Console database files, Baseline profiles, and Security
          profiles are always backed up during an update.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="install-post">
    <title>Post-Installation Notes</title>
    <para>Once the product is installed, you should perform a scan using a profile of your choice. Then analyze the
      results, referencing the <emphasis>OS Lockdown Modules Guide</emphasis>, and make a backup of your system. Take
      the following precautionary steps prior to performing your first apply: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para> System Administrators should change their passwords. </para>
        <para> This is important because many profiles include a module (&ldquo;Set Password Aging on Active
          Accounts&rdquo;) that sets password aging which could result in those accounts being locked. This only applies
          to local <filename>/etc/passwd</filename> accounts. Note that the module now includes options to limit which
          accounts are subject to the password aging restriction. If this module is applied where account passwords have
          been changed with the permitted time period, users (including system users such as root) might not be able to
          log in. </para>
        <para/>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ensure that at least one user (not counting root) is in the wheel group (Linux only). </para>
        <para> The “Limit Access to Root From Su” module limits the use of the <filename>su(1)</filename> command to
          only users within the wheel group. This module now includes an option to enforce this behavior even if there
          are no regular users who are also members of the wheel group. </para>
        <para/>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Console is not always a console (Linux only). </para>
        <para>The &ldquo;Root Console Only Logins&rdquo; module prevents direct root login unless you are on a device
          listed in the <filename>/etc/securetty</filename> file. See the <emphasis role="bold">securetty</emphasis> man
          page for additional information. This module now includes an option to specify the list of devices that are
          considered secure and suitable for direct root login. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</appendix>
