<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % CommonEntities SYSTEM "../COMMON_ENTITIES.ent">
%CommonEntities;
]>
<appendix version="5.0" xml:id="app-known-issues" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <!--<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="docbook.css"?>-->
  <title>Known Issues and Workarounds</title>
  <section xml:id="rel-issues-ssl">
    <title>Potential Issue with Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6 and openSSL</title>
    <para>There is a known issue that can occur if your OS Lockdown Console is using Java 1.7 and certain versions of
      the openssl 1.0.1e libraries. See <link xlink:href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1022017"
        >https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1022017</link> for additional details. The issue occurs when a
      client machine attempts to contact the OS Lockdown Console (for example, registering a client or trying to send a
      notification to the OS Lockdown Console) with an error similar to the following: </para>
    <para>
      <literallayout>SSL routines:SSL23_GET_SERVER_HELLO:tlsv1 alert internal error</literallayout>
    </para>
    <para>Three possible solutions are as follows: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Reconfigure the OS Lockdown Console to use 'high-strength' ciphers with:</para>
        <screen>/usr/share/oslockdown/tools/SB_Setup -c</screen>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Install the Java 1.6 runtime and reconfigure the OS Lockdown Console to use it with:</para>
        <screen>/usr/share/oslockdown/tools/SB_Setup -c</screen>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Upgrade the version of openssl being used on the OS Lockdown Console machine</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="rel-issues-modules">
    <title>OS Lockdown Modules</title>
    <section xml:id="rel_issues-grub">
      <title>Require GRUB Password</title>
      <para>The &ldquo;Require GRUB Password&rdquo; module is currently explicitly looking for a line in the
          <filename>grub.conf</filename> file that starts with <filename>password --md5 HASH</filename>, where
          <filename>HASH</filename> is the MD5 hash of the actual grub passphrase. If a guideline is looking for a
        different hashing requirement, for example the Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6 DISA STIG (line item RHEL-06-000068)
        which requires <filename>password --encrypted "$6$HASH"</filename>, this module can indicate a problem even
        though the <filename>grub.conf</filename> file is correctly configured. </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="rel-issues-lockacct">
      <title>Account Locks and Mandatory Screen Saver</title>
      <para>A problem has been identified with the &ldquo;Lock Account after Three Failed Login Attempts&rdquo; module
        on some Linux platforms. The changes implemented by this module do not correctly lock accounts after the failure
        count has been exceeded. </para>
      <para>DISA has been contacted (TMS Action Request CSD-AR001850790) to request clarification on how to fix this
        module to pass the GEN000460 requirement. While this module does not perform correctly, it does not cause
        additional harmful effects, except when combined with the &ldquo;Set Mandatory Screen Saver&rdquo; module. When
        both modules are active, regular users are unable to authenticate to any screen saver preventing the screen
        saver to unlock. </para>
      <para>A potential workaround is available for users who are required to implement both modules. This workaround
        has not yet been approved by DISA, and exempts the screensaver from the &ldquo;Lock Account after Three Failed
        Login Attempts&rdquo; module. This exemption must be explained to your accreditor. Refer to <xref
          linkend="unlocking-the-screensaver" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle"/> for the workaround. </para>
    </section>
    <!-- ********************************************************************** -->
    <section xml:id="rel-issues-password-policy-modules">
      <title>Password Policy Modules</title>
      <para>Some password policy related modules may not properly reverse or undo their settings after an apply has been
        performed due to module ordering. Most users resolve this issue by performing a second undo action. </para>
    </section>
    <!-- ********************************************************************** -->
    <section xml:id="rel-issues-novell-suse10-sp-utility">
      <title>Modules Require a Special Utility in Novell SUSE 10 SP3</title>
      <para>In <trademark class="registered">Novell</trademark>
        <trademark class="registered">SUSE</trademark> 10 SP3, the following OS Lockdown modules require the use of a
        special utility (the utility is not present in Novell SUSE 10 SP3, but it is present in its counterpart,
        openSUSE 10.3): </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para> Password Policy Length Minimum </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> Password Policy Numeric Minimum </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> Password Policy Special Characters </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> Password Policy Uppercase Minimum </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>If operational processes permit, the openSUSE <filename>pam-config</filename> package can be installed in
        the Novell SUSE 10 SP3 environment. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
  <section xml:id="rel-issues-console">
    <title>OS Lockdown Console</title>
    <section xml:id="rel-issues-jre">
      <title>Java Runtime Environment Version</title>
      <para>Note that the OS Lockdown Console requires a <trademark>Java</trademark> 1.6 or Java 1.7 JRE. Some
        distributions may not provide a Java 1.6 or 1.7 JRE on the installation media. Examples of this are certain
        Novell SUSE 10, openSUSE 10 and Red Hat Enterprise Linux 4 distributions. For these platforms, it is recommended
        to download and use Oracle’s official Java 1.6 or Java 1.7 JRE when installing the OS Lockdown Console. If
        deploying the OS Lockdown Console on Linux instances running on the IBM System z mainframe, use the IBM-provided
        Java 1.6 or 1.7 packages. </para>
      <para>If Java from the Oracle website has been installed on Novell SUSE or openSUSE distributions, warning
        messages may appear when the OS Lockdown Console starts. Depending on your version of SUSE/openSUSE and Oracle
        Java packages, you may see a message similar to the following when the <filename>chkconfig</filename> command is
        run: </para>
      <para>
        <literallayout>
            <filename>insserv: Script jexec is broken: incomplete LSB comment. insserv: missing
              `Required-Stop:' entry: please add even if empty.</filename>
          </literallayout>
      </para>
      <para>The cause seems to be a file installed by the Oracle Java packages. This message can be safely ignored. For
        more information, refer to <link xlink:href="https://bugzilla.novell.com/show_bug.cgi?id=504596"
          >https://bugzilla.novell.com/show_bug.cgi?id=504596</link>. </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="rel-issues-error-display">
      <title>Intermittent Error Display Issue</title>
      <para> When the OS Lockdown Console is talking to the client on a different subnet, the red Status Bar does not
        display, only the pop-up message displays. The error can be viewed in the
          <filename>/var/lib/oslockdown/logs/osl-console.log</filename> log file. </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="rel-issues-zseries-firefox">
      <title>Console Connection Issues with Firefox and IBM System z</title>
      <para> Issues exist using <trademark class="registered">Firefox</trademark> to connect to the OS Lockdown Console
        running on the zSeries. It appears to be due to the supported cipher suites available with the Java packages
        installed. <trademark class="registered">Internet Explorer</trademark> does not appear to have this issue.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>zSeries Java Issues</title>
      <para> Two issues were identified with some IBM-supplied Java 1.6 JRE environments. At this point it is not known
        if they apply to the IBM-supplied Java 1.7 JRE environments as well. Refer to <xref
          linkend="zseries-extended-high-cpu" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle"/> and <xref
          linkend="zseries-java-traceback" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle"/> for details.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref linkend="zseries-extended-high-cpu" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle"/> addresses a case where the
            Java process can cause high CPU utilization for an extended length of time. An IBM support article is
            provided for additional information, as well as a workaround for the OS Lockdown Console. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <xref linkend="zseries-java-traceback" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle"/> addresses an issue that can
            cause the OS Lockdown Console to display a “JVMVRFY012 stack shape inconsistent” error. IBM has identified a
            problem with the 1.6 JRE in SR10 and earlier that should be fixed in the SR11 release (scheduled for summer
            2012). IBM has developed an iFix for this specific issue. Contact your IBM vendor and request information on
            PMR 66499,001,866. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</appendix>
