<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % CommonEntities SYSTEM "../COMMON_ENTITIES.ent">
%CommonEntities;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="deploy-planning" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
   xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <!--<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="docbook.css"?>-->
   <title>Deployment Planning</title>
   <indexterm>
      <primary>OS Lockdown</primary>
      <secondary>Deployment</secondary>
   </indexterm>
   <indexterm>
      <primary>Deployment</primary>
      <secondary>Prerequisites</secondary>
   </indexterm>
   <indexterm>
      <primary>Global Zones</primary>
   </indexterm>
   <para>This chapter lists the prerequisites required prior to deploying OS Lockdown.</para>
   <note>
      <para>Solaris Zones and OS Lockdown</para>
      <para>A global zone comprises the entire system and is equivalent to a normal Solaris operating system instance.
         It has access to the physical hardware and can see and control all processes. Inside the global zone are
         non-global zones. These zones are isolated from the physical hardware characteristics of the machine.</para>
      <para>There are two basic types of non-global zones: <emphasis role="bold">whole root</emphasis> and <emphasis
            role="bold">sparse root</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>A whole root zone includes a complete copy of the operating system on disk.</para>
      <para>A sparse root zone does not include its own copy of the operating system binaries and libraries. This means
         it does not have copies of the <filename>/usr</filename>, <filename>/sbin</filename>,
            <filename>/platform</filename>, or <filename>/lib</filename> directories. Instead, programs in the
         non-global zone use the files that reside in the global zone via loopback file system (LOFS) mount
         point.</para>
   </note>
   <warning>
      <para>Note that part of OS Lockdown installs in the <filename>/usr/</filename> file system which is shared as
         read-only to a sparse root zone. Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> install OS Lockdown in a sparse root zone. Only
         install OS Lockdown in a global zone or a whole root non-global zone. Also, do not change the installation
         location when installing OS Lockdown.</para>
   </warning>
   <important>
      <para>Currently, OS Lockdown has been officially tested on Solaris 10 U3-U9. In May 2011, Oracle released patches
         143506-02 and 143507-02 which removed the <trademark>Python</trademark> 2.4.4 development libraries and
         installed Python 2.6 as the primary Python version. OS Lockdown has been modified to work in this environment,
         but due to the licensing restrictions placed by Oracle on obtaining these patches and more recent versions of
         Solaris 10, additional testing has not been performed. Limited testing by end-users with Solaris 10 update 10
         installations show the modifications are working as intended. </para>
   </important>
   <section xml:id="sb-deploy-steps">
      <title>Required: OS Lockdown Deployment Steps</title>
      <important>
         <para>The following steps are <emphasis role="italic">required</emphasis> prior to deploying both OS Lockdown
            editions (Enterprise and Standalone).</para>
      </important>
      <note>
         <para>Execute all commands with root permissions.</para>
      </note>
      <para>Perform the following deployment steps:</para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
         <listitem>
            <para>Select the server hardware and coordinate network connectivity. Refer to <xref
                  linkend="console-hardware" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle"/> for details.<indexterm>
                  <primary>MAC Address</primary>
               </indexterm><indexterm>
                  <primary>Deployment</primary>
                  <secondary>Instructions</secondary>
               </indexterm></para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Select the correct web browser versions and configure them. Refer to <xref
                  linkend="recommended-web-browsers" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle"/> for a list of recommended
               web browsers.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Determine whether your system meets the following requirements:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>OS Lockdown requires <trademark>Java</trademark> v1.6 or v1.7.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>If you are using Solaris, patch 121606-04+ for SPARC or 121607-04+ for x86 systems (updates
                     Python to 2.4 or higher).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>If you are using Solaris, the operating system must have American English language support to include 8-bit Universal
                     Character Set (UCS)/Unicode Transformation Format (UTF-8). For Solaris systems, this means the
                     &ldquo;SUNWeu8os&rdquo; package must be installed.</para>
                  <para>To determine if a system has the proper language support, execute the following command:</para>
                  <para>
                     <screen># <userinput>/usr/bin/locale -a |/bin/grep -i en_US.utf</userinput></screen>
                  </para>
                  <para>Verify that either <filename>en_US.utf8</filename> or <filename>en_US.UTF-8</filename> is
                     returned. If the command returns nothing, then the language support must be installed.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>If you are upgrading a v4.0.8 or earlier OS Lockdown Console, it is recommended that you use the
               graphical interface to export the database prior to installing new software. Refer to <xref
                  linkend="enterprise-mig" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle"/> for details.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Install and configure the OS Lockdown application. Refer to <xref linkend="install-config"
                  xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle"/> for details.</para>
         </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
   </section>
   <section xml:id="console-hardware">
      <title>OS Lockdown Console Hardware</title>
      <para>The OS Lockdown Console is capable of managing thousands of clients. The scanning, configuring, and
         baselining work is performed on each client. The OS Lockdown Console, however, must have enough disk space to
         store client reports and enough physical memory and processing power to aggregate reports for large groups of
         clients and to perform report comparisons.</para>
      <para>It is recommended that you have at least a P4 2.0 GHz or <trademark>Sun</trademark>
         <trademark class="registered">UltraSPARC</trademark> III processor. For OS Lockdown Consoles a minimum of 1 GB of physical memory is 
	 recommended. For larger deployments, 2 GB or more physical memory is recommended.<indexterm>
            <primary>OS Lockdown Console</primary>
            <secondary>Memory Increase</secondary>
         </indexterm>
      </para>
      <note>
         <para>If the OS Lockdown Console reports an &ldquo;out of memory&rdquo; error, even though you have enough
            physical memory, increase the memory allocated to the OS Lockdown Console during start up.</para> <para>To increase the
            memory, edit the following section in the <filename>/usr/share/oslockdown/console/bin/setenv.sh</filename>
            file:</para>
         <screen># Set Memory Size startup size
JAVA_OPTS="$JAVA_OPTS -Xmx512M"
export JAVA_OPTS</screen>
      </note>
      <para>The amount of disk space required is dependent on the number of clients, the frequency of report creation,
         and how long the reports must be archived. For OS Lockdown Consoles managing fewer than 500 clients and are
         generating reports on a weekly basis, 4 GB of storage is recommended. Otherwise, 8 GB or more of storage is
         recommended. In both scenarios, a six month archive is assumed. </para>
      <indexterm>
         <primary>Deployment</primary>
         <secondary>Storage Space</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>The console-to-client communications is SOAP-based TLSv1 encrypted and authenticated. When the OS Lockdown
         Console is requested (or scheduled) to perform an action, it pushes small profiles (up to 20 or 30 KB) to the
         clients. When the action is complete, the OS Lockdown Console receives notification that reports are available.
         When the OS Lockdown Console retrieves reports, it retrieves Baseline reports (6-8 MB), Assessment reports
         (&gt;1 MB), Apply reports (&gt;1 MB), and Undo reports (&gt;1 MB).</para>
   </section>
   <section xml:id="recommended-web-browsers">
      <title>Recommended Web Browsers</title>
      <para>The preferred web browsers for the OS Lockdown Console in OS Lockdown v2.0 and later are:</para>
      <indexterm>
         <primary>Web Browsers</primary>
         <secondary>Recommended</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
         <primary>Browsers</primary>
         <secondary>Recommended</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
         <primary>Firefox</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
         <primary>Internet Explorer</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
         <primary>TLS</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
         <primary>Security</primary>
         <secondary>TLS</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para><trademark class="registered">Firefox</trademark> 3 and higher</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para><trademark class="registered">Internet Explorer</trademark> 7 and higher</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Since the OS Lockdown Console uses Transport Layer Security (TLS) for encryption, you must enable it.</para>
      <indexterm>
         <primary>Transport Layer Security (TLS)</primary>
         <secondary>Enabling</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <procedure xml:id="procedure-enable-tls-firefox">
         <para>To enable TLS in Firefox:</para>
         <step>
            <para>Select <emphasis role="bold">Tools</emphasis> &gt; <emphasis role="bold">Options</emphasis>. The
                  <emphasis role="bold">Options</emphasis> page displays.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>Click the <emphasis role="bold">Advanced</emphasis> icon.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>Click the <emphasis role="bold">Encryption</emphasis> tab. </para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>Select the <emphasis role="bold">Use TLS 1.0</emphasis> checkbox.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis>.</para>
         </step>
      </procedure>
      <procedure xml:id="procedure-enable-tls-ie">
         <para>To enable TLS in Internet Explorer:</para>
         <step>
            <para>Select <emphasis role="bold">Tools</emphasis> &gt; <emphasis role="bold">Internet Options</emphasis>.
               The <emphasis role="bold">Internet Options</emphasis> page displays.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>Click the <emphasis role="bold">Advanced</emphasis> tab.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>Select the <emphasis role="bold">Use TLS 1.0</emphasis> checkbox.</para>
         </step>
         <step>
            <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis>.</para>
         </step>
      </procedure>
   </section>
</chapter>
