<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: app-passwd-policy-enforcing.xml 23964 2017-03-21 21:04:23Z acochrane $ -->
<section version="5.0" xml:id="app-passwd-policy-enforcing" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
 <title>Enforcing the Policy</title>
 <para> Implementing a <link linkend="app-passwd-policy-aging">password aging</link> and <link
   linkend="app-passwd-policy-composition">password length and composition</link> policy applies to accounts when a new
  password is set. When introducing a new policy or changing an existing one, current active accounts must adhere to the
  new policy. Since these accounts set the password prior to implementing the policy, they have inherited the previous
  policy. OS Lockdown offers a module to <link linkend="SetPassAgingOnAccts">Set Password Aging on Active
   Accounts</link>. </para>
 <para> Consider disallowing the secure shell service from accepting empty passwords in conjunction with the <link
   linkend="NoEmptyPasswords">No Empty Passwords</link> module. OS Lockdown’s <link linkend="SshdDisableEmptyPasswords"
   >SSHD Disable Empty Passwords</link> will ensure this policy is enforced. </para>
 <para> Furthermore, consider disabling services which allow passwords to be transmitted over unencrypted network
  connections. Failure to do so could result in disclosure of passwords. Consider using the following OS Lockdown
  modules: </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <link linkend="DisableFTP_vsftpd">Disable FTP (vsftpd)</link>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <link linkend="DisableFTP_gssftp">Disable FTP (gssftp)</link>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <link linkend="DisableTelnet">Disable Telnet</link>
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para> Finally, appropriate discretionary access controls should be applied to configuration files to prevent
  unauthorized changes to the password policy. Consider using the following OS Lockdown modules to secure configuration
  files: </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <link linkend="PasswdPerms">Password Perms</link>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <link linkend="SysConfigFilePerms">System Configuration File Permissions</link>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <link linkend="SecureSetXIDFiles">Secure SUID/SGID Executables</link>
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</section>
