<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="AuditToolsPerms">
  <title xml:id="fileDACs">Audit Tools Perms</title>
  <para>
  Restricts the use of the audit tool commands by ensuring the indicated
  files are owned by the correct user/group, with permissions no greater
  than the supplied Discretionary Access Controls (DACs) values.
 </para>
  <para>
  If it is impractical to limit the use of these commands to root,
  consider setting the group owner to
  <emphasis role="italic">wheel</emphasis> and setting the group execute
  bit. This will allow system administrators to use the commands.
  <indexterm><primary>wheel</primary></indexterm>
 </para>
  <important>
    <para>
   SUID/SGID bits are not considered here. If a command should be
   SUID/SGID, then the bits must be set manually (if not already set)
   and the command added to
   <filename>/var/lib/oslockdown/files/suid_whitelist.custom</filename>
   or
   <filename>/var/lib/oslockdown/files/sgid_whitelist.custom</filename>
   as appropriate.
  </para>
  </important>
  <simplesect xml:id="AuditToolsPerms-compliancy">
    <title>Compliancy</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DISA Red Hat 5 STIG (V1R17)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     GEN002715 - System audit tool executables must be owned by root.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     GEN002716 - System audit tool executables must be group-owned by
     root, bin, sys, or system.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     GEN002717 - System audit tool executables must have mode 0750 or
     less permissive.
    </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
  <simplesect xml:id="AuditToolsPerms-options">
    <title>Module Options</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>List of files/directories<emphasis><para>List of files/directories to process.  May have wild card expansion (using shell globbing rules) available if the module supports it.  If empty, no file checks will be done.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Expand wildcards (shell globbing)?<emphasis><para>Allow for wildcard expansion using shell globbing rules.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Allowed User Names<emphasis><para>List of user names (ignored if empty). If '&lt;SYSTEM;&gt;' is in the list, then the list of all local privileged accounts will be inserted <emphasis>at this position</emphasis>, with duplicate names removed.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Allowed Group Names<emphasis><para>List of group names (ignored if empty). If '&lt;SYSTEM;&gt;' is in the list, then the list of all local privileged group accounts will be inserted <emphasis>at this position</emphasis>, with duplicate names removed.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Maximum allowed permissions<emphasis><para>Maximum permitted Discretionary Access Controls (DACs) in <emphasis>octal</emphasis> format (i.e.,  max perms is 777 or 0777).
      Note that only the read/write/execute bits are considered.  Note also that if a directory has read permissions for 
      user/group/other allowed, then execute permissions for user/group/other are <emphasis>also</emphasis> allowed to allow for directory traversal.  No extra permissions are enforced, just allowed.  If empty, no permissions checks will be done.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
</section>
