<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="AuditRules">
  <title xml:id="Auditing">Audit Rules</title>
  <para>
  Configures the audit subsystem to record relevant security events such
  as administrative actions, file access, file deletions, login, logout,
  session initiations, and access control changes.
  <footnote xml:id="mcdougall"><para>
    McDougall, Richard and Jim Mauro. <emphasis role="underline">Solaris
    Internals: Solaris 10 and OpenSolaris Kernel
    Architecture</emphasis>. Santa Clara, CA: Sun Microsystems Press,
    2007.
   </para></footnote>
 </para>
  <para>
  The audit rules configuration must be finely tuned to balance the
  number of recorded events against system performance needs. An
  overload of event records can occur and substantially reduce system
  performance. This rules set will not be initialized until the audit
  subsystem is restarted, so it is safe to apply the change and review
  the rules manually.
  <indexterm><primary>audit.rules</primary></indexterm>
 </para>
  <para>
  Using the
  “<xref linkend="AuditLogRotation" xrefstyle="select: title"/>”
  module with this module is strongly recommended.
 </para>
  <informaltable cellpadding="2" cellspacing="2" frame="all">
    <tgroup cols="3">
      <colspec align="left" colname="c1" colwidth="0.8*"/>
      <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="0.8*"/>
      <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="1.0*"/>
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Operating Systems</entry>
          <entry>Configuration Files</entry>
          <entry>Settings</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody valign="middle">
        <row>
          <entry>Fedora 10, 11, 12, and 13</entry>
          <entry morerows="4">
            <filename>/etc/audit/audit.rules</filename>
          </entry>
          <entry morerows="4">Industry-standard profiles provide auditing rules.
      <indexterm><primary>.profile</primary></indexterm></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 4</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 5</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>SUSE 10 and 11</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
  <simplesect xml:id="AuditRules-options">
    <title>Module Options</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Kernel auditing rules.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
  <simplesect xml:id="AuditRules-compliancy">
    <title>Compliancy</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>CAG 20 Critical Security Controls (v2.3)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>CC-11 - Account Monitoring and Control</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CC-6 - Maintenance, Monitoring, and Analysis of Audit Logs</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>CIA DCID 6/3 (May 2000)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.1.b(2)(a) - Auditing - Date and time entity performed system action</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.1.b(2)(d)(1) - Auditing - Record Successful and unsuccessful logons and logoffs</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.1.b(2)(d)(2) - Auditing - Record accesses to security-relevant objects</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.1.b(2)(d)(3) - Auditing - Record activities at the system console</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.2.a(4)(d)(1) - Auditing - Record Successful and unsuccessful logons and logoffs (PL2)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.2.a(4)(d)(2) - Auditing - Record accesses to security-relevant objects (PL2)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.2.a(4)(d)(3) - Auditing - Record activities at the system console (PL2)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.3.a(7) - Auditing - Record changes to the mechanism's list of user formal access permissions (PL3)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DHS Linux Configuration Guidance (2010.8)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>5 - Audit Trail</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DISA Red Hat 5 STIG (V1R17)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002720 - The audit system must be configured to audit failed attempts to access files and programs.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002720-2 - The audit system must be configured to audit failed attempts to access files and programs.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002720-3 - The audit system must be configured to audit failed attempts to access files and programs.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002720-4 - The audit system must be configured to audit failed attempts to access files and programs.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002720-5 - The audit system must be configured to audit failed attempts to access files and programs.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002740 - The audit system must be configured to audit files and programs deleted by the user.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002740-2 - The audit system must be configured to audit file deletions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002750 - The audit system must be configured to audit account creation.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002751 - The audit system must be configured to audit account modification.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002752 - The audit system must be configured to audit account disabling.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002753 - The audit system must be configured to audit account termination.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002760-10 - The audit system must be configured to audit all administrative, privileged, and security actions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002760-2 - The audit system must be configured to audit all administrative, privileged, and security actions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002760-3 - The audit system must be configured to audit all administrative, privileged, and security actions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002760-4 - The audit system must be configured to audit all administrative, privileged, and security actions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002760-5 - The audit system must be configured to audit all administrative, privileged, and security actions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002760-6 - The audit system must be configured to audit all administrative, privileged, and security actions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002760-7 - The audit system must be configured to audit all administrative, privileged, and security actions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002760-8 - The audit system must be configured to audit all administrative, privileged, and security actions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002760-9 - The audit system must be configured to audit all administrative, privileged, and security actions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820-10 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820-11 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820-12 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820-13 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820-2 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820-3 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820-4 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820-5 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820-6 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820-7 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820-8 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820-9 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002825 - The audit system must be configured to audit the loading and unloading of dynamic kernel modules.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002825-2 - The audit system must be configured to audit the loading and unloading of dynamic kernel modules - delete_module.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002825-3 - The audit system must be configured to audit the loading and unloading of dynamic kernel modules - /sbin/insmod.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002825-4 - The audit system must be configured to audit the loading and unloading of dynamic kernel modules -/sbin/modprobe.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002825-5 - The audit system must be configured to audit the loading and unloading of dynamic kernel modules - /sbin/rmmod</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DISA Red Hat 6 STIG (V1R14)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000165 - The audit system must be configured to audit all attempts to alter system time through adjtimex.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000167 - The audit system must be configured to audit all attempts to alter system time through settimeofday.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000169 - The audit system must be configured to audit all attempts to alter system time through stime.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000171 - The audit system must be configured to audit all attempts to alter system time through clock_settime.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000173 - The audit system must be configured to audit all attempts to alter system time through /etc/localtime.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000174 - The operating system must automatically audit account creation.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000175 - The operating system must automatically audit account modification.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000176 - The operating system must automatically audit account disabling actions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000177 - The operating system must automatically audit account termination.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000182 - The audit system must be configured to audit modifications to the systems network configuration.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000183 - The audit system must be configured to audit modifications to the systems Mandatory Access Control (MAC) configuration (SELinux).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000184 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications using chmod.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000185 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications using chown.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000186 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications using fchmod.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000187 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications using fchmodat.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000188 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications using fchown.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000189 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications using fchownat.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000190 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications using fremovexattr.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000191 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications using fsetxattr.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000192 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications using lchown.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000193 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications using lremovexattr.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000194 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications using lsetxattr.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000195 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications using removexattr.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000196 - The audit system must be configured to audit all discretionary access control permission modifications using setxattr.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000197 - The audit system must be configured to audit failed attempts to access files and programs.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000198 - The audit system must be configured to audit all use of setuid and setgid programs.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000199 - The audit system must be configured to audit successful file system mounts.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000200 - The audit system must be configured to audit user deletions of files and programs.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000201 - The audit system must be configured to audit changes to the /etc/sudoers file.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RHEL-06-000202 - The audit system must be configured to audit the loading and unloading of dynamic kernel modules.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DISA UNIX STIG (v5 R1.30)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002720 - Audit Failed File and Program Access Attempts</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002740 - Audit File and Program Deletion</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002760 - Audit Administrative, Privileged, and Security Actions</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002800 - Audit Login, Logout, and Session Initiation</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN002820 - Audit Discretionary Access Control Permission Modifications</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DoD JAFAN 6/3 (Oct 2004)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.1.b(2)(a) - Auditing - Date and time entity performed system action</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.1.b(2)(d)(1) - Auditing - Record Successful and unsuccessful logons and logoffs</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.1.b(2)(d)(2) - Auditing - Record accesses to security-relevant objects</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.1.b(2)(d)(3) - Auditing - Record activities at the system console</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.2.a(4)(d)(1) - Auditing - Record Successful and unsuccessful logons and logoffs (PL2)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.2.a(4)(d)(2) - Auditing - Record accesses to security-relevant objects (PL2)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.2.a(4)(d)(3) - Auditing - Record activities at the system console (PL2)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>4.B.3.a(7) - Auditing - Record changes to the mechanism's list of user formal access permissions (PL3)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DoD NISPOM (Feb 2006)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>8.303a - Unique Identification</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>8.602a1 - Automated Audit Trail Creation</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>8.602d1 - Audit 4 Requirements</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>NERC Cyber Security - Systems Security Management (CIP-007-3)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>CIP-007-3-R5.1.2 - Generate logs of sufficient detail to create historical audit trails of individual user account access</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>NIST FISMA (SP 800-53)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>AU-10 - Non-repudiation</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>AU-2 - Auditable Events</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>AU-3 - Content of Audit Records</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>AU-8 - Time Stamps</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>NSA Guide to the Secure Configuration of RHEL5 (Rev. 4.2 / Aug 2011)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>2.6.2.4 - Configure auditd Rules for Comprehensive Auditing</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>NVD CCE</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>CCE-4075-8 - Kernel level auditing for administrative actions should be enabled or disabled as appropriate</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CCE-4600-3 - Kernel level auditing for file attribute modification should be enabled or disabled as appropriate</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CCE-4610-2 - Kernel level auditing for root login/logout should be enabled or disabled as appropriate</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CCE-4679-7 - Kernel level auditing for login/logout should be enabled or disabled as appropriate</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>PCI DSS (v2.0)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>10.1 - Link all access to system components to each individual user</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>10.2.2 - Audit Events: All actions taken by any individual with root or administrative privileges</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>10.2.3 - Audit Events: Access to all audit trails</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>10.2.7 - Audit Events: Creation and deletion of system-level objects.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>10.3.1 - Audit Events: User identification</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>10.3.2 - Audit Events: Type of event</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>10.3.3 - Audit Events: Date and time</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>10.3.4 - Audit Events: Success or failure indication</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>10.3.5 - Audit Events: Origination of event</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>10.3.6 - Audit Events: Identity or name of affected data, system component</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>2.2 - Configuration standards for system components consistent with industry-accepted system hardening standards</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
</section>
