<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: CheckXdNxSupport.xml 24135 2017-11-07 16:13:34Z rsanders $ -->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="CheckXdNxSupport" version="5.0">
  <title xml:id="HardwareServices">Check Kernel for XD/NX Support</title>
  <para>
  Scan-only module, which checks the running Linux kernel to see if it
  supports Execute Disable (XD) or No Execute (NX).
 </para>
  <para>
  Later 32-bit processors in the x86 family support the ability to
  prevent code execution on a per memory page basis. Generically and on
  AMD processors, this ability is called No Execute (NX), while on
  Intel® processors it is called Execute Disable (XD). This ability can
  help prevent exploitation of buffer overflow vulnerabilities and
  should be activated whenever possible. Extra steps must be taken to
  ensure that this protection is enabled on 32-bit x86 systems. Other
  processors, such as Itanium®, POWER™, and 64-bit x86 (both AMD64 or
  Intel 64), have included such support since inception and the standard
  kernel for those platforms supports the feature.
 </para>
  <para>
  This module examines the <filename>/proc/cpuinfo</filename> file for
  any CPUs which have the 'PAE' and 'NX' flag set. If these flags are
  set, the module will use the <filename>uname(1)</filename> utility’s
  <filename><emphasis role="italic">-r</emphasis></filename> option to
  determine the running kernel’s name. If the name does not end with
  the string “PAE”, it is assumed the current kernel does not
  support PAE so the module will report a failure. This module will only
  scan the system, so it is the responsibility of the system
  administrator to install the “kernel-PAE” package and boot the
  system using a PAE-enabled kernel.
 </para>
  <simplesect xml:id="CheckXdNxSupport-compliancy">
    <title>Compliancy</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>NSA Guide to the Secure Configuration of RHEL5 (Rev. 4.2 / Aug 2011)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>2.2.4.4 - Enable Execute Disable (XD) or No Execute (NX) Support on 32-bit x86 Systems</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>NVD CCE</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>CCE-4172-3 - Kernel support for the XD/NX processor feature should be enabled or disabled as appropriate</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
</section>
