<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="ConfigureAuditdConf">
  <title xml:id="Auditing">Configure /etc/audit/auditd.conf Settings</title>
  <para>
  Verify that the indicated lines are contained in the
  <filename>/etc/audit/auditd.conf</filename> file. Note that the
  specific settings vary between guidelines and also can change based on
  site requirements. OS Lockdown does not perform checks here except
  that the lines below are or are not present in the
  <filename>auditd.conf</filename> file with the required settings.
  Lines missing (or with different settings) will be added/corrected
  when applied. Note that on Red Hat Enterprise Linux 4 systems the
  <filename>/etc/auditd.conf</filename> file may be examined rather than
  the <filename>/etc/audit/auditd.conf</filename> file.
 </para>
  <simplesect xml:id="ConfigureAuditdConf-compliancy">
    <title>Compliancy</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DISA Red Hat 5 STIG (V1R17)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     GEN002719 - The audit system must alert the SA in the event of an
     audit processing failure.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     GEN002730 - The audit system must alert the SA when the audit
     storage volume approaches its capacity.
    </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DISA Red Hat 6 STIG (V1R14)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000005 - The audit system must alert designated staff
     members when the audit storage volume approaches capacity.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000159 - The system must retain enough rotated audit logs
     to cover the required log retention period.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000160 - The system must set a maximum audit log file size.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000161 - The system must rotate audit log files that reach
     the maximum file size.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000163 - The audit system must switch the system to
     single-user mode when available audit storage volume becomes
     dangerously low.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000311 - The audit system must provide a warning when
     allocated audit record storage volume reaches a documented
     percentage of maximum audit record storage capacity.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000313 - The audit system must identify staff members to
     receive notifications of audit log storage volume capacity issues.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000510 - The audit system must take appropriate action when
     the audit storage volume is full.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000511 - The audit system must take appropriate action when
     there are disk errors on the audit storage volume.
    </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
  <simplesect xml:id="ConfigureAuditdConf-options">
    <title>Module Options</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>List of setting (one per line, "NAME VALUE")</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
</section>
