<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="ConsultRPMDatabase">
  <title xml:id="fileDACs">Consult the RPM Database for file/directory Setting</title>
  <para>
  Use the information in the system RPM database to verify the various
  attributes (such as ownership, permissions, and MD5 signatures) of the
  files/directories for all installed packages. This module can detect
  places where the settings are invalid and call upon RPM to restore
  certain settings. Some attributes can only be restored by
  re-installing the associated packages, which is beyond the scope of
  this module. As well, this module can be told not to change some
  discrepancies, for example places where OS Lockdown has made other
  changes to the system, or where certain RPMs or files/directories are
  required to be changed.
 </para>
  <formalpara>
    <title>Exemptions</title>
    <para>
   RPM has the concept of 'configuration' files, which are expected to
   change from what is originally installed. By default this module will
   exempt such files from the MD5 signature check. If the file is
   <emphasis role="italic">missing</emphasis> however, this will be
   flagged as a potential problem.
  </para>
    <para>
   Specific RPMs can be entered to ignore, such as the case of an RPM
   whose internal defaults are wrong, or one where the files are
   modified after being installed.
  </para>
    <para>
   Specific files or directories can also be entered to ignore. Note
   that if a directory is entered, it is <emphasis>not</emphasis>
   treated recursively, so only the directory itself (not the contents)
   will be ignored.
  </para>
  </formalpara>
  <important>
    <para>
   This module uses the RPM to detect places where the RPM database is
   not in agreement with what is actually on file. However, rather than
   just asking RPM to resolve these problems, each inconsistency is
   evaluated to see if a change should be made. Part of this is to allow
   for system administrators to make an accommodation for instances
   where specific RPMs, files, or directories
   <emphasis role="italics">need</emphasis> to have settings that differ
   from what was installed. In addition, other OS Lockdown modules may
   make changes to installed files and directories (for example
   <link linkend="SecureUnownedFiles">Remove Unowned Files</link> which
   set unowned files to root:root ownership and permissions of 000) that
   would be undone by asking RPM to restore those settings. In cases
   where this module is told not to take action, a message to that
   effect is always logged.
  </para>
    <para>
   To mitigate those potential issues, the behavior of this module can
   be fine tuned using the options provided below.
  </para>
    <para>
   Please make changes to these options carefully, as the changes can
   directly impact the security posture of your system.
  </para>
  </important>
  <simplesect xml:id="ConsultRPMDatabase-compliancy">
    <title>Compliancy</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DISA Red Hat 6 STIG (V1R14)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000278 - The system package management tool must verify
     permissions on all files and directories associated with the audit
     package.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000279 - The system package management tool must verify
     ownership on all files and directories associated with the audit
     package.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000280 - The system package management tool must verify
     group-ownership on all files and directories associated with the
     audit package.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000281 - The system package management tool must verify
     contents of all files associated with the audit package.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000516 - The system package management tool must verify
     ownership on all files and directories associated with packages.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000517 - The system package management tool must verify
     group-ownership on all files and directories associated with
     packages.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000518 - The system package management tool must verify
     permissions on all files and directories associated with packages.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     RHEL-06-000519 - The system package management tool must verify
     contents of all files associated with packages.
    </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
  <simplesect xml:id="ConsultRPMDatabase-options">
    <title>Module Options</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Should files owned by root/root with permissions of 000 be left alone?<emphasis><para>If OS Lockdown needs to remove a file or entry (for example, if an unowned file is found) the 
            ownership it set to root:root, and the permissions are set to 000.  This module would undo every single one of those
            changes unless told to allow those changes to persist.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>List of RPM packages to ignore</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>List of specific files/dirs to ignore (dirs are treated non-recursively), one entry per line</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
</section>
