<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="DisableFileShare" version="5.0">
  <title xml:id="FileSharingServices">Disable File Sharing Networks</title>
  <para>
  Peer-to-peer transfer services allow for the anonymous transfer of
  files. If not configured correctly, your system files may become
  writable. This module will disable the executables and connection
  daemons for most of the file sharing networks available to Linux.
 </para>
  <para>
  This module searches for the following executables in most standard
  directories: <filename>apollon, bittorrent, bittorrent-console,
  bittorrent-curses, giftd, gift-gnutella, gift-setup, gtk-gnutella,
  LimeWire.jar, mlbt, mldc, mldonkey, mlgnut, mlslsk, nap,
  napping,</filename> and <filename>qtella</filename>. If found, the
  permissions will be set to zeros.
  <indexterm><primary>bittorrent</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm><primary>console</primary></indexterm>
 </para>
  <para>
  Some of the clients for file sharing networks that run on Windows®
  will also work on Linux if launched using Wine. It is suggested that
  unless Wine is necessary for your environment, it should be disabled.
 </para>
  <simplesect xml:id="DisableFileShare-compliancy">
    <title>Compliancy</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>CAG 20 Critical Security Controls (v2.3)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>CC-13 - Limitation and Control of Network Ports, Protocols, and Services</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CC-3 - Secure Configurations for Hardware and Software on Laptops, Workstations, and Servers</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DISA Red Hat 5 STIG (V1R17)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN006040 - The system must not have any peer-to-peer file-sharing application installed.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DISA UNIX STIG (v5 R1.30)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN006040 - Peer-to-Peer Application Authorization with DAA</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>NERC Cyber Security - Electronic Security Perimeters (CIP-005-3)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>CIP-005-3-R2.2 - Enable only ports and services needed for operations</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>NERC Cyber Security - Systems Security Management (CIP-007-3)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>CIP-007-3-R2.2 - Disable ports and services not needed for operations</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>PCI DSS (v2.0)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>2.2.2 - Disable all unnecessary and insecure services</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
</section>
