<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="DisableKernelSprt_fstypes" version="5.0">
  <title xml:id="Filesystems">Disable Mounting of Uncommon Filesystem Types</title>
  <para>
  Prevents the kernel from loading modules for uncommon file system
  types. When the kernel does not load the associated module, the system
  will not support the file system type and will not be able to mount
  that type.
 </para>
  <para>
  This modules will examine all files in
  <filename>/etc/modprobe.d</filename> and the
  <filename>/etc/modprobe.conf</filename> file (if they exist) and look
  for the line(s) that are specified as arguments. If a line is found
  that matches the first two whitespace separated fields but not the
  remainder, then it will be updated to match the provided lines. If no
  matching line is found, then it will be added to either
  <filename>/etc/modprobe.d/oslockdown_modprobe_settings</filename> (if
  <filename>/etc/modprobe.d</filename> is a directory), or to
  <filename>/etc/modprobe.conf</filename>.
 </para>
  <para>
  This module is not applicable to Oracle Solaris.
 </para>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>/etc/modprobe.conf</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <simplesect xml:id="DisableKernelSprt_fstypes-options">
    <title>Module Options</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Required lines to disable Firewire kernel module(s)<emphasis><para>One or more lines that can disable or otherwise alter how kernel modules are loaded/configured/disabled.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
  <simplesect xml:id="DisableKernelSprt_fstypes-compliancy">
    <title>Compliancy</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>NSA Guide to the Secure Configuration of RHEL5 (Rev. 4.2 / Aug 2011)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>2.2.2.5 - Disable Mounting of Uncommon Filesystem Types</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>NVD CCE</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>CCE-14089-7 - Support for cramfs filesystems should be enabeld or disabled as appropriate.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CCE-14093-9 - Support for hfsplus filesystems should be enabeld or disabled as appropriate.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CCE-14118-4 - Support for squashfs filesystems should be enabeld or disabled as appropriate.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CCE-14457-6 - Support for freevxfs filesystems should be enabeld or disabled as appropriate.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CCE-14853-6 - Support for jffs2 filesystems should be enabeld or disabled as appropriate.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CCE-14871-8 - Support for udf filesystems should be enabeld or disabled as appropriate.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CCE-15087-0 - Support for hfs filesystems should be enabeld or disabled as appropriate.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
</section>
