<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="EnableKernelExecShield" version="5.0">
  <title xml:id="General">Enable ExecShield Kernel Module</title>
  <para>
  The Linux kernel provides a number of features to provide protection
  against buffer overflows and provide address space randomization.
  These features include random placement of the stack and other memory
  regions, prevention of execution in memory that should only hold data,
  and special handling of text buffers. These features should be on by
  default; however, this module will also ensure it is implicitly in
  <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename>.
  <indexterm><primary>/etc/sysctl.conf</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm><primary>Files and Directories</primary><secondary>/etc/sysctl.conf</secondary></indexterm>

  <indexterm><primary>ExecShield</primary></indexterm>

  <indexterm><primary>sysctl.conf</primary></indexterm>
 </para>
  <para>
  Please refer to your kernel documentation for more information on
  these features, and look in the <filename>/proc/sys/kernel</filename>
  pseudo-directory for additional settings that can be altered.
 </para>
  
  <simplesect xml:id="EnableKernelExecShield-options">
    <title>Module Options</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Required settings for /etc/sysconf.conf, one per line &lt;param&gt; = &lt;valuegt;</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
<simplesect xml:id="EnableKernelExecShield-compliancy"><title>Compliancy</title><itemizedlist><title>DISA Red Hat 5 STIG (V1R17)</title><listitem><para>GEN003540 - The system must implement non-executable program stacks.</para></listitem><listitem><para>GEN008420 - The system must use available memory address randomization techniques.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist><title>DISA Red Hat 6 STIG (V1R14)</title><listitem><para>RHEL-06-000078 - The system must implement virtual address space randomization.</para></listitem><listitem><para>RHEL-06-000079 - The system must limit the ability of processes to have simultaneous write and execute access to memory.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist><title>NSA Guide to the Secure Configuration of RHEL5 (Rev. 4.2 / Aug 2011)</title><listitem><para>2.2.4.3 - Enable ExecShield</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist><title>NVD CCE</title><listitem><para>CCE-4146-7 - ExecShield randomized placement of virtual memory regions should be enabled or disabled as appropriate</para></listitem><listitem><para>CCE-4168-1 - ExecShield should be enabled or disabled as appropriate</para></listitem></itemizedlist></simplesect></section>
