<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="SambaPasswordFilePerms" version="5.0">
  <title xml:id="fileDACs">Samba Password File Permissions</title>
  <para>
  Restricts the ownership and group ownership of the files and/or
  directories below, as well as what maximum set of Discretionary Access
  Controls (DACs) are allowed. The list of files/directories may have
  options for looking recursively or performing wildcard expansion on
  names.
 </para>
  <simplesect xml:id="SambaPasswordFilePerms-compliancy">
    <title>Compliancy</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DISA Red Hat 5 STIG (V1R17)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     GEN006160 - The /etc/smbpasswd file must be owned by root.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     GEN006180 - The smbpasswd file must be group-owned by root.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     GEN006200 - The smbpasswd file must have mode 0600 or less
     permissive.
    </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DISA UNIX STIG (v5 R1.30)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     GEN006160 - smbpasswd Ownership
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     GEN006180 - smbpasswd Group Ownership
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     GEN006200 - smbpasswd Permissions
    </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>NIST FISMA (SP 800-53)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     AC-3 - Access Enforcement
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     AU-9 - Protection of Audit Information
    </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>PCI DSS (v2.0)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
     2.2 - Configuration standards for system components consistent with
     industry-accepted system hardening standards
    </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
  <simplesect xml:id="SambaPasswordFilePerms-options">
    <title>Module Options</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>List of files/directories<emphasis><para>List of files/directories to process.  May have wild card expansion (using shell globbing rules) available if the module supports it.  If empty, no file checks will be done.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Allowed User Names<emphasis><para>List of user names (ignored if empty). If '&lt;SYSTEM;&gt;' is in the list, then the list of all local privileged accounts will be inserted <emphasis>at this position</emphasis>, with duplicate names removed.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Allowed Group Names<emphasis><para>List of group names (ignored if empty). If '&lt;SYSTEM;&gt;' is in the list, then the list of all local privileged group accounts will be inserted <emphasis>at this position</emphasis>, with duplicate names removed.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Maximum allowed permissions<emphasis><para>Maximum permitted Discretionary Access Controls (DACs) in <emphasis>octal</emphasis> format (i.e.,  max perms is 777 or 0777).
      Note that only the read/write/execute bits are considered.  Note also that if a directory has read permissions for 
      user/group/other allowed, then execute permissions for user/group/other are <emphasis>also</emphasis> allowed to allow for directory traversal.  No extra permissions are enforced, just allowed.  If empty, no permissions checks will be done.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
</section>
