<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="TcpWrappers" version="5.0">
  <title xml:id="NetworkConfig">Enable TCP Wrappers</title>
  <para>
  Verifies the <filename>/etc/hosts.allow</filename> and
  <filename>/etc/hosts.deny</filename> access control files are setup
  correctly for TCP Wrappers. Both files will be examined for required
  lines, owned by the allowable user/group combination, and with
  acceptable permissions. If any of the fields are blank, then those
  checks will be ignored.
 </para>
  <para>
  Each line in the
  <filename><emphasis role="italic">Required...</emphasis></filename>
  options will be processed independently, and if that line is not found
  <emphasis>as is</emphasis> in the associated file, then it will
  trigger either a scan failure or that line will be appended to the
  file. Should any text field be blank, then checks for that field will
  be skipped.
 </para>
  <simplesect xml:id="TcpWrappers-options">
    <title>Module Options</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Allowed User Names<emphasis><para>List of user names (ignored if empty). If '&lt;SYSTEM;&gt;' is in the list, then the list of all local privileged accounts will be inserted <emphasis>at this position</emphasis>, with duplicate names removed.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Allowed Group Names<emphasis><para>List of group names (ignored if empty). If '&lt;SYSTEM;&gt;' is in the list, then the list of all local privileged group accounts will be inserted <emphasis>at this position</emphasis>, with duplicate names removed.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Maximum allowed permissions<emphasis><para>Maximum permitted Discretionary Access Controls (DACs) in <emphasis>octal</emphasis> format (i.e.,  max perms is 777 or 0777).
      Note that only the read/write/execute bits are considered.  Note also that if a directory has read permissions for 
      user/group/other allowed, then execute permissions for user/group/other are <emphasis>also</emphasis> allowed to allow for directory traversal.  No extra permissions are enforced, just allowed.  If empty, no permissions checks will be done.</para></emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Required lines for /etc/hosts.allow</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Required lines for /etc/hosts.deny</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
  <simplesect xml:id="TcpWrappers-compliancy">
    <title>Compliancy</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>DISA Red Hat 5 STIG (V1R17)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN005540 - The SSH daemon must be configured for IP filtering.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>GEN006620 - The system's access control program must be configured to grant or deny system access to specific hosts.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>NSA Guide to the Secure Configuration of RHEL5 (Rev. 4.2 / Aug 2011)</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>2.5.4.1 - How TCP Wrapper Protects Services</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>
</section>
